Henry T. Becker Papers 1984.0004
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Henry T. Becker Papers
undated, 1917-1989
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0004
16 Linear Feet
Henry T. Becker was born in Hartford, Connecticut. He attended George Washington University, Duquesne University, Western Reserve University and the University of Connecticut. Becker had a long and distinguished labor career beginning with Lodge 1746 of the International Association of Machinists while working for Pratt & Whitney Aircraft in East Hartford. He was also affiliated with the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, American Federation of Teachers, Greater Hartford Labor Council, Connecticut State Labor Council, and other state-wide boards.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Mr. Becker to the University of Connecticut Libraries in several accessions beginning in March 1984.
Arrangement
Series I: Personal (1917-1983) contains primarily biographical information, including correspondence, documentation of political activities, and articles and papers written by Becker.
Series II: Correspondence (1975-1980) consists of letters written by Becker during his affiliation with the Connecticut State Labor Council, the Greater Hartford Labor Council and the United Way.
Series III: Unions (undated, 1941-1983) is divided into six subseries—A: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (1950-1974); B: American Federation of Teachers (1955-1979); C: Connecticut State Labor Council (1957-1983); D: Greater Hartford Labor Council (1973-19834); E: International Association of Machinists (1941-1983); F: United Labor Agency (1978-1983). The series contains correspondence, publications, news releases, strikes, local and regional activity notices, reports, policies, proposals, minutes and other materials pertaining to Becker's union activities.
Series IV: Memorabilia(undated, 1940-1989) contains photographs of Becker during his youth, army and political career, and union and community services. It also contains plaques, buttons, programs, newspapers and clippings. The union movie, "Look for the Union Label" is located in this series.
Biography
Henry T. Becker was born on 5 February 1917 in Hartford, Connecticut. He attended George Washington University, Duquesne University, Western Reserve University and the University of Connecticut.
Becker had a long and distinguished labor career beginning with Lodge 1746 of the International Association of Machinists while working for Pratt & Whitney Aircraft in East Hartford. In 1946, he was appointed steward, and from 1947-1949 conducted classes for stewards and local officers in Labor History while working as a full-time organizer.
In January 1950, Becker accepted the position of national representative in the union label department of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. For the next decade, he worked on and directed campaigns against non-union clothing firms. While on leave of absences from the ACWA, 1956-1958, Becker worked as the national representative and organizer for the American Federation of Teachers. During this time, he reorganized and made permanent the Connecticut Federation of Teachers.
In 1965 he became a delegate to the Greater Hartford Labor Council for Local 125 of the ACWA, and in 1973 was appointed a member of the Community Services Committee, eventually becoming the executive secretary of the committee. Becker's affiliation with the Connecticut State Labor Council began in 1958. In the late 1960s he helped formulate the bylaws for the Connecticut State Union Label and Service Trades Council, of which he was later elected secretary-treasurer. In 1974, Becker assisted in forming the Statewide Community Services Committee.
In addition to his work with labor unions, Becker has been involved with politics and community activities in Connecticut. As a long time member of the Manchester Democratic Town Committee, he was elected Democratic Chairman of District Two in 1960, a post he held until 1962. In 1966, he was elected to the General Assembly, representing District 20 in the town of Manchester. From 1957 to 1966, he was Chairman of the Pension Board of the Town of Manchester. In the 1970s and 1980s, he also served as a member of the Statewide Health Coordinating Advisory Committee of the School of Social Work, University of Connecticut, and the Board of Directors of the Connecticut Lion's Eye Research Foundation.
Henry Becker is a veteran of the U. S. Army Air Corps (1943-1945), a member of the American Legion, the Knights of Columbus, and the Manchester Lions Club. He is married to Marie Elizabeth De La Chevrotiere Becker, and the father of three children, Theresa, Elaine and Timothy.
Additional biographical information may be found in Series I of the Papers.
Scope and Content
The collection documents Becker's career with various unions and service organizations. There is a small quantity of personal materials, but very little information concerning his political activities. The collection includes correspondence, reports, publications, news releases, proposals, minutes, and ephemera.
Personal papers; Labor movement; Notes; Correspondence; Connecticut (state); Reports; Publications (documents); Moving images; Financial Records; Labor unions--Officials and employees; Photographs; Labor unions-Organizing; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; American Federation of Teachers; International Association of Machinists; AFL-CIO. Connecticut State Labor Council; AFL-CIO. Greater Hartford Labor Council; United Labor Agency
- Series I: Personal, 1917-1983
  - Biographical and family, 1917-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Political, 1949-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Benefits
    - Amalgamated staff retirement plan, 1946-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Amalgamated benefits, 1962-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Krushchev and labor leaders, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Labor Participation Committee, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Writings and notes, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal expenses: U.L.A. representative, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1975-1980
  - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1976 January - March (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1976 April - May (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1976 November - December (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1979 January - February (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1979 March - April (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1979 May - July (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1979 August - October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1979 November - December (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1980 January - March (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1980 April - November (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series III: Unions, undated, 1950-1983
  - Subseries A: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, undated, 1950-1975
    - General correspondence, 1950-1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Cleveland correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Farah strike
      - The Advance, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
        - Union periodicals, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        - Union publications, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Viva la Huelgo, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - Fact sheets, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Unidentified, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - New releases, 1973 [?] (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - General subject, 1963-1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Hyde Park Boycott
      - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Labor Council meetings, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Press releases, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Publications, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Reports, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Subseries B: American Federation of Teachers, 1955-1979
    - General subject and correspondence, 1955-1979 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Regional local
      - California
        - Officer's report, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 41)
        - Publications, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Connecticut Federation of Teachers
        - Hartford County Council, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 43)
        - Legislation, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 44)
        - Mailing list, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 45)
        - Minutes of meetings, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - Rhode Island
        - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Rochester, New York
        - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 48)
        - General subject, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 49)
        - Legislative committee, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 50)
        - Publications, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Waterbury, Connecticut
        - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Reports: Becker's organizer and expense account, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Union Employee
      - Bochstohler, Peter
        - Correspondence and organizer's reports, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - Clark, Henry
        - Organizer's reports, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Union President
      - Megel, Carl J.
        - Correspondence, 1955-1962 (Box 2, Folder 55-60)
        - Reports to Megel, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 61-62)
  - Subseries C: Connecticut State Labor Council, undated, 1957-1983
    - Agendas and minutes, 1973-1982 (Box 2, Folder 63-64)
    - Community service correspondence, 1967-1982 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - General subject and constitution, 1957-1982 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Ideas for institutes, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Connecticut State Union Label and Service Trade Council
      - Constitution, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - Correspondence, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - Minutes of meetings, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - Meeting programs, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - General correspondence, 1958-1983 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Annual convention, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Employment and Training Committee, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Executive board, 1976-1981 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Operation fuel, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Subseries D: Greater Hartford Labor Council (GHLC), 1973-1983
    - CETA proposal, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Department income maintenance correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - General correspondence—community services, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Meeting agendas, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1974-1981 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Reports, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - General correspondence, 1973-1984 (Box 2, Folder 83-85)
    - Urgent business correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Financial reports—secretary-treasurer, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Financial statements, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - General subject file
      - United Way/GHLC/AFL-CIO agreement, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 89)
      - Unidentified, 1975-1982 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      - Proposals and resolutions, 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 91)
      - Vargas, Ed (GHLC president), 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Bylaws Committee minutes, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Committee on Political Education minutes, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Delegates
      - Agendas, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 95)
      - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 96)
      - Minutes, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Education and Social Issues committee agenda, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Executive Board
      - Agendas, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      - Minutes, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - GHLC minutes, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Membership—general subject, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Minutes (handwritten), 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Subseries E: International Association of Machinists, undated, 1941-1983
    - Correspondence—boycott of United Way, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1975 (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - District 91 agreement, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 107)
    - District 91 retirement club correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 108)
    - General subject, 1941-1981 (Box 1, Folder 109)
    - Hourly wage rate, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 110)
    - Lodge 354 agreements, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 111)
    - Lodge 354 elections, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 112)
    - Lodge 1746
      - Correspondence, 1949-1980 (Box 1, Folder 113)
      - Filing of charges, undated (Box 1, Folder 114)
      - General subject, undated, 1949, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 115)
      - Material for stewards classes, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 116)
      - Monthly and weekly reports, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 117)
      - Pratt & Whitney contracts, 1946-1974 (Box 1, Folder 118)
      - Suggestions to Pratt & Whitney, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 119)
    - Reports
      - General subject, undated, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 120)
      - Machinist News, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 121)
        - Executive Board and Shop committee materials, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Subseries F: United Labor Agency, 1974-1983
    - Community service, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 123)
    - Contracts, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 124)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 125-129)
    - Evaluation of CT United labor community, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 130)
    - Expeditor program, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 131)
    - Financial records, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 132)
    - Legal papers
      - Appointment of statutory agent for service, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 133)
      - Bylaws, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 134)
      - IRS applications, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 135)
      - Incorporation papers, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 136)
      - Request for grant of funds, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 137)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 138)
    - Organization and first biennial report, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 139)
    - Policies and proposals
      - Handicapped placement projects, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 140)
      - Plans for the Capital area, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 141)
      - Policies, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 142)
      - Proposed changes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 143)
      - Proposed United Labor Agency, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 144)
    - Reports, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 145)
    - Unfinished business, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 146)
- Series IV: Memorabilia, undated, 1940-1989
  - Photographs, 1940-1980 (Box 1, Folder 147-148)
  - AFL-CIO publications and bylaws, 1956-1983 (Box 1, Folder 149)
  - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America leaflets, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 150)
  - Award dinner programs, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 151)
  - General subject
    - Business cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 152)
    - Leaflets, 1969-1982 (Box 1, Folder 153)
  - Greater Hartford Labor Council leaflets, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 154)
  - International Association of Machinists
    - Lodge 1746 leaflets, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 155-156)
    - Ephemera, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 157)
  - Personal memorabilia, 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - Labor memorabilia, 1940-1969 (Box 4, Folder 159-164)
  - Political memorabilia, 1960-1989 (Box 4, Folder 165-166)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1946-1982 (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - ACWA leaflets (oversize), 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 168)
  - Labor newspapers: Labor News, Labor Daily, Connecticut Vanguard, 1953-1960 (Box 5, Folder 169)
  - ACWA 21st Biennial convention photograph, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 170)
  - Motion picture: "Look for the Union Label", 1955 [?]; 2 reels (Box 5, Folder 171)